<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A persvvasion to the English recusants, to reconcile themselues to the Church of England Written for the better satisfaction of those which be ignorant. By Iohn Doue Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Dove, John, 1560 or 61-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845725</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1234:22, 1446:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A persvvasion to the English recusants, to reconcile themselues to the Church of England Written for the better satisfaction of those which be ignorant. By Iohn Doue Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Dove, John, 1560 or 61-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By V[alentine] S[immes] for Cuthbert Burby dvvelling in Paules church-yard at the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of recusancie.</note>
                  <note>British Library copy identified as STC 7084 on UMI microfilm reel 1234.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1234 (British Library copy) and at reel 1446 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177853:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177853:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PERSWASION to the Engliſh Recuſants, to Reconcile <hi>themſelues to the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Written for the better ſatisfaction of thoſe which be ignorant.</p>
            <p>By Iohn Doue Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <bibl>PSAL. 72.</bibl>
            <q>Giue thy iudgement to the King, O God, and thy righteouſnes to the Kings ſonne.</q>
            <bibl>1. PET. 2.</bibl>
            <q>Feare God, Honour the King.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>emblem of man walking</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by V. S. for Cuthbert Burby dvvelling in Paules church-yard at the ſigne of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177853:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177853:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the moſt High and Mighty Prince, IAMES by the grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France and Ireland,</hi> Defendour of the Faith.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ratious and dread Soueraigne,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I ſay the truth, I lie not, my conſcience bearing me witnes in the Holy-ghost, that I haue with the Apostle great heauineſſe, and continuall ſorrow in my heart for many of my brethren and Country-men. And my hearty deſire and prayer for them to God, is, that they may be ſaued. For I beare them recorde, that they haue the zeale of God, though not according to knowledge, which is the onely cauſe that mooued me to write this ſhort Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. And, becauſe God of his great goodneſſe hath vouchſafed your tender yeeres the education of <hi>TIMOTHIE,</hi> and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your Highneſſe, ſince your happy gouernement with princely gifts, knowledge to diſcerne truth, and zeale to maintaine truth, I humbly preſent vnto your Maiestie, theſe few lines, containing a ſubiect of ſo great importance. The common voyce, and hope
<pb facs="tcp:177853:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> of your beſt affected people is, that your Highneſſe hath a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intent, to make God yet better knowne in <hi>IVDA,</hi> and his name yet greater in <hi>HIERVSALEM,</hi> to bring all theſe your Kingdomes to the acknowledgement and profeſsion of one truth; ſo that hereafter <hi>HIERVSALEM</hi> may be as a walled towne and fenced citty, which is at vnitie within it ſelfe: and as it was in the dayes of the <hi>IVDGES,</hi> all <hi>ISRAEL</hi> may be gathered together, as one man, from <hi>DAN</hi> to <hi>BEERSHEBA,</hi> vnto the Lord in <hi>MISHPAH.</hi> The Lord guide and proſper you in all your wayes, the Lord establiſh your houſe and kingdome, the Lord bleſſe you out of <hi>SION,</hi> that you may ſee the wealth of <hi>HIERVSALEM</hi> all the dayes of your life, that you may ſee your Childrens Children, and peace in <hi>SION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Maieſties humble Subiect, IOHN DOVE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177853:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶A Perſwaſion to the Engliſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>ſants, to reconcile themſelues to</hi> the Church of England.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>It is not enough for them to pray priuatly, but it is alſo required, that they ioyne in prayer with the Congregation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the prayers of the faithfull are heard, if they be faithfully made, in what places ſoeuer, becauſe our Sauiour ſaith: <note place="margin">Matthew 7</note> Whoſoeuer asketh, he ſhall receiue, and therefore, not the Publican onely was <note place="margin">Luke 18 2. Reg. 20</note> heard in the Temple, but alſo King <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias</hi> in his Chamber, <hi>Elias</hi> vnder the Iuniper tree, <hi>Ionas</hi> in the bottome of the Sea, <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in the priſon: Yet the Church is a place more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iona 2 oratio Manaſſis.</hi> Matth 21.</note> appoynted for prayer, it is called the houſe of prayer, and God is more peculiarly preſent in that houſe, than in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther houſes. Of the Temple we reade, that Gods eyes were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen towards that houſe night and day, his name was eſpecially <note place="margin">1. Reg. 8</note> there, he harkened to the prayers of his Seruants which ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed foorth their handes in that place, and of them which were in captiuitie, if they turned towardes that houſe which was built for his name. A greater promiſe is made to the prayers of many v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited together, than of one, and a more fauourable preſence of Chriſt amongſt them which make their ioynt petition; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that when a congregation is ioyned together in his <note place="margin">Matth 18</note> name, he will be in the midſt of them, and if they agree in earth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177853:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpon any thing, whatſoeuer they ſhall deſire, it ſhall be giuen of his Father which is in heauen.</p>
               <p>If we lay before our eyes the Stories of the Bible, the exerciſe <note place="margin">2. Ezra 8</note> of the godly was ſuch. In the dayes of <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe it was ſo: All the people aſſembled themſelues together, hee brought the booke of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> before the aſſembly of men and women, and all that could heare and vnderſtand; he read from morning vntill mid-day vnto them, the eares of all the people harkened to the booke of the Law, he preached to them out of a woodden Pulpit, he praiſed the Lord the great God, and al the people anſwered, AMEN, AMEN, with lifting vp their hands, and they bowed themſelues, and worſhipped the Lorde with their faces towards the ground. In the newe Teſtament their maner was to meete together on the Saboth day, to ioyne in prayer, and to heare the word preached, and to receiue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. In the Acts of the Apoſtles at <hi>Antiochia</hi> was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <note place="margin">Act. 14</note> a Lecture of the Law and the Prophets. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered words of exhortation there after the Lecture, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him to preach to them the ſame ſermon againe the next Saboth. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and his company being at <hi>Philippi</hi> on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both <note place="margin">Act. 17</note> day, went out of the Citty by a riuer where they were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to pray, there he preached and conuerted <hi>Lydia.</hi> And no doubt, but if our Recuſants would heare our Sermons, many of them alſo would be conuerted. Vpon the Lords day at <hi>Troas</hi> the <note place="margin">Act. 20</note> diſciples were gathered together, to break bread, a multitude was gathered together, and <hi>Paul</hi> preached to them. When <hi>Peter</hi> was in priſon, the Church making a ioynt petition for him, obtained a <note place="margin">Act. 12</note> ſpeedy and miraculous deliuery. And it was obſerued as an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall vertue in the primitiue Church, that they continued toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in prayer and breaking of bread, and that they had all one heart. And to this purpoſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth them ſaying: I beſeech you brethren, in the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that <note place="margin">1. Corin. 1.</note> ye all ſpeake one thing, that ye be knit together in one mind and iudgement. And againe; the God of patience and conſolation <note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> graunt, that you may be like-minded one to another according to Chriſt Ieſus, that you with one mind, and one mouth, praiſe God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The true markes of the viſible Church of God, are the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177853:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the word, the participation of the ſacraments and publike prayer, as out of the ſcriptures I haue declared. Let vs therefore examine the groundes whereupon ſo many of our nation, which would eſpecially be accounted of the true church, withdrawe themſelues from our publike aſſemblies, refuſe to ioyne with vs in ſo Chriſtian exerciſes; inſomuch, that whereas it was wont to be reputed a puniſhment to be interdicted, ſuſpended, and like Lepers, to be ſhut out of the Congregation, they now like Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers exclude themſelues. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> needeth not now to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> for hee will excommunicate himſelfe, <note place="margin">Sozoſ. li. 7 c. 24</note> and we haue as much neede to whip them into the Temple, as our Sauiour had to whippe them out, as hee did in the ſtorie of the Goſpel. They alleadge for themſelues, they do communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> together in prayer, though not with vs; they haue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles and Maſſes in their chambers, and the exerciſe of their owne religion; but that it is againſt their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to come to our churches, that we are Heretikes, Sciſmatikes, not members of the Catholike Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not at vnity among ourſelues, and conſequently, that they may not ſafely communicate with vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of conſcience.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe ignorant Recuſant being perſwaded by the Miniſter, or required by the Magiſtrate, to ſhew his conformitie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Lawes, by reſorting to the pariſh-Church, where he dwelleth: when hee is not able to anſwere ſuch arguments as are obiected againſt him, nor in any ſorte to defend his owne Religion, pretendeth his Conſcience, and ſaieth: It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Vide Gre. Mar. in tract de ſchi.</note> my conſcience, to come to your Church, and whatſoeuer I doe againſt my conſcience, is ſinne. I confeſſe that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is done without teſtimonie and warrant of conſcience, is ſin to them which doe it, be the thing which is done, in it ſelfe neuer ſo lawfull, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith: He that doubteth, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned if he eate, becauſe he eateth not of faith; and whatſoeuer <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> is not of faith, is ſinne. In which wordes, by faith is vnderſtood Conſcience. But by the way, they muſt ſee that their conſcience be rightly informed, elſe it will be their damnation. For, as <note place="margin">Matth. 26. Act 9</note>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:177853:5"/> it was ſinne in Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to deny Chriſt, when in his conſcience hee know that hee did euill: ſo it was ſinne in Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Chriſt, when hee thought in his conſcience hee did well. Therefore, it is not onely damnable to do contrary to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but alſo to doe according as their conſcience ſhall direct them, if they be not perſwaded by the truth. Therefore, let them not deceiue themſelues, taking that for conſcience, which is but an error of conſcience, and indeede a falſe perſwaſion of their minds, in follovving that which the ignorance of their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies and blinde conceites doth leade them vnto, without ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further. For ſo in his zeale <hi>Vzza</hi> ſupported the Arke <note place="margin">1. Chron. 13</note> when it was ready to fall, his conſcience perſvvading him that he did wel, although it vvas diſpleaſing vnto God. So ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 22</note> ſpeaketh of himſelfe, that he vvas zealous tovvardes God vvhen he perſecuted, and ſo our Sauiour fore-warneth his diſciples, that <note place="margin">Iohn 16</note> men ſhall excommunicate them, that the time ſhall come, that whoſoeuer killeth them, ſhall thinke hee doth God good ſeruice; and hee ſheweth the reaſon of this their error. Theſe things ſaith hee, they will doe vnto you, becauſe they haue not knowne the Father, nor me.</p>
               <p>Therefore, for their better inſtruction, I wil define vnto them what Conſcience is. Conſcience, I ſay, is an application of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall knowledge grounded vppon Gods word to particular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and intents. Or thus: conſcience is a kinde of argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or practike ſyllogiſme, whereby, out of a generall propoſition, we doe, by a particular concluſion, abſolue or condemne our ſelues, or others. In this ſyllogiſme, the <hi>maior</hi> propoſition is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſe and feeling of Gods iudgements, whereby we do rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and diſcourſe of our actions, intents and purpoſes, hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the rule of the lawe of God. The <hi>minor</hi> is the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of our actions, intents, and purpoſes, according to that rule, the concluſion is our finall determination concerning our ſelues or others, what wee or they hauing thus done, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and purpoſed, are to deeme or iudge of our ſelues or them. So then, in our conſcience firſt we diſcourſe, then we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and laſt of all wee determine. For example. In <hi>Dauids</hi> taking <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rias</hi> his wife, we may ſee what <hi>Dauids</hi> conſcience was. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> Firſt, he had this generall notion imprinted in his minde, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177853:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> grounded vpon <hi>Exodus,</hi> that adulterie was damnation: and if <note place="margin">Exod. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> when he entended to take <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rias</hi> his wife, he had examined his intent by the rule of <hi>Exodus,</hi> hee had found it to be adulterie: and thirdly, after due examination had, finding his intent to bee adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, hee could not but condemne himſelfe in his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he was guiltie of damnation. According to this ſenſe <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> They haue the effect of the Lawe written in their hearts, their conſcience alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts accuſing or excuſing one an other.</p>
               <p>Albeit conſcience is ſometimes taken only for the intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power and facultie of our vnderſtanding &amp; reaſonable ſoule, by which we are able thus to argue and diſcourſe with our ſelues: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; Wee muſt obey Magiſtrates for conſcience <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> ſake; that is, becauſe of our owne reaſon, knowledge, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which reuealeth ſo much light vnto vs: GOD will eternally puniſh diſobedience, and therefore it ſhall not be ſafe for vs to charge and burthen our ſoules with the wrath of God. Sometimes for the <hi>minor</hi> alone, which is the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our actions and intents, whether they be good or euill: ſo the Apoſtle ſaith of himſelfe; <hi>Nihil mihi conſcius ſum,</hi> I knowe nothing of my ſelfe, yet I am not thereby iuſtified; that is, I know no hainous crime wherewith I ſhould be touched. Sometimes <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> for the concluſion alone, ſo he ſaith: I haue in all good conſcience ſerued God vntill this day; that is, I do abſolue my ſelfe from any <note place="margin">Act. 23.</note> grieuous crime that I haue committed.</p>
               <p>Now, the Recuſants argue in this maner: No Heretikes nor Sciſmatikes are to be communicated withall, but Proteſtants are Heretikes and Sciſmatikes, and therefore not to bee commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated withall. Their <hi>maior</hi> propoſition is vndoubtedly true, becauſe it is grounded vpon ſcripture, <hi>Titus</hi> the third? Reiect him that is an Heretike after two or three admonitions: and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle; Bid him not God ſpeede: and <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. Marke them diligently which make diuiſion, and auoyde them. The error therefore, is in the <hi>minor</hi> or examination of this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of communicating with vs according to that generall rule, that no ſocietie is to be had with Heretikes: for whereas they ſay wee are Heretikes, it is not true. Neither is it maruell though our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants haue erred concerning vs, ſeeing that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177853:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> Diſciples haue erred concerning the like. When the ſheete was <note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> let downe, wherein were all manner of beaſtes, and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was bidden to ariſe, kill, and eate: Hee anſwered: Not ſo Lorde: for I neuer ate any meate that was vncleane. And therefore hee argued in this manner: No vncleane meates are to bee eaten: But theſe meates are vncleane, therefore they are not to be eaten. The <hi>Maior</hi> was true, becauſe grounded vppon <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 11. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. where the differences of meates are ſet downe. But in his <hi>Minor</hi> he was deceiued, which thought thoſe meates to be vncleane, for as much as vnder the Goſpel, the difference of meats was taken away, and no meate was polluted, in reſpect of the conſcience of man. So then, as it was not Saint <hi>Peters</hi> conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but the errour of his conſcience, when he refuſed the meates as vncleane, which God had ſanctified and made lawfull; ſo it is not their conſcience, but the error of their conſcience that they refuſe vs for ſchiſme &amp; hereſie, which indeed are true goſpellers and members of the myſticall body of Ieſus Chriſt, as by Gods aſſiſtance I wil proue. And as the Diſciples, not knowing of <hi>Pauls</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> conuerſation, were afraide to ioyne with him, ſuppoſing him to be a perſecuter when he was a Preacher: ſo they feare to ioyne with vs, ſuppoſing vs to be in the wrong way, whereas indeed we be in the right.</p>
               <p>And becauſe I haue ſaide, it is not vpon conſcience that they ſequeſter themſelues from vs, I will ſhew them how many wayes a mans conſcience may erre and be deceiued, and ſo carried away from the truth, and they are theſe eight following. The firſt is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſo the common ſort ignorantly alledge we are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, that our religion is not warrantable, but cannot know what hereſie is, neither yet rightly conceiue the groundes either of our religion of their owne. For they are inhibited to heare our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <note place="margin">Vide Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Trid. &amp; Pref. in indicem expurg. &amp; Greg. Mart. de ſchiſ.</note> to reade our bookes, to haue conference with vs, or to be catechized by vs. How then ſhould they knowe our religion? They are nouriſhed in blindneſſe by their owne teachers, which hold it as a principle, that it is fit they ſhould be ignorant. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they permitted to haue the Bible in their mother tongue. How then can they know their owne religion? They are vnfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and vtterly deſtitute of all meanes and helpes which may bring them to be able to diſcerne truth from hereſie.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:177853:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The ſecond is negligence. So they which in ſome meaſure are learned, doo call vs heretikes, which can, but doo not reade our bookes, although they haue them, nor examine the groundes which wee hold, although they are able, and it is permitted vnto them. Concerning their owne doctrine, they are contented to receiue it for truth, vpon the credit of others without further proofe, and to ſee with other mens eyes, heare with other mens eares, ſpeake with other mens tongues, becauſe they will not ſpend ſo much time as to ſearch further, and what ſlaunder ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they doo heare of vs, they are readie to beleeue it. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <note place="margin">Edm. Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p. rat. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Campion</hi> ſlandereth our Church, as if we did offer violence to the holy ſcriptures, affirming that <hi>Luther</hi> wrote contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his Epiſtle: his diſciples bluſh not to report the ſame, becauſe hee hath written it, without further enquirie, whether hee writ the truth or not, whereas if they would but vouchſafe to examine the place for their owne ſatisfaction, they would finde it a ſlaunder, which they becauſe of their ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe do holde for a truth. They are contented to buy <hi>Campion</hi> alone, and <hi>Gregorie Martine</hi> his Preface, with the notes of the Seminaries of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> vpon the New Teſtament, and now and then to reade them. But as for Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi> his anſwere, many of them ſuffer it not to be in their ſtudies, or if it bee in the Catalogue of their liberarie, they do not reade it. And as for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Fulkes</hi> anſwere to <hi>Gregorie Martines</hi> Preface, and the notes of the Seminaries, they are ſo farre from conferring the one with the other, that ſo they might be ſatisfied and reſolued of the truth, as they are contented to giue more mony for the Rhemiſh Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alone, then for the ſame booke with Doctor <hi>Fulkes</hi> anſwer ioyned with it.</p>
               <p>The third is obſtinacie. For, as the firſt cannot, becauſe they be ignorant and vnable to iudge, and depriued of all meanes by which they may be enabled; and the ſecond do not iudge right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they are ſlouthfull, and loth to take ſo much paines as to trie the ſpirites, to examine doctrine, and conferre places: So the third ſort of men will not vnderſtand the truth, becauſe they be obſtinate, they will reſiſt the holy Ghoſt, and ſtop their eares againſt the truth, as the adder doth againſt the charmer, and as the Iewes did againſt Saint <hi>Stephen.</hi> Wee ſhall not perſwade <note place="margin">Act. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177853:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> them although wee doo perſwade them, becauſe inſtruction and <note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> faith commeth by hearing, they wil not heare leaſt they ſhould be inſtructed, and beleeue the truth. They ſay their fathers profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that religion, and therefore they will rather erre with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <note place="margin">Gen. 31.</note> than embrace the truth with vs: like <hi>Rachel,</hi> which would not leaue behinde her the gods of her Father, but carrie them with her. They were brought vp and inſtructed in this religion from their childhood, and now they ſay they will not alter. They <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> forgot the rule of the Apoſtle, which willeth them to make try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of all, and then to hold that which is beſt. For they will heare none, they will holde what they haue held, and they will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the better. And in ſo doing, what do they but as <hi>Pharao</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note> did, who ſaide: Who is the Lord, that I ſhould heare his voice, and let <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe? I know not the Lord, neither will I let <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe. Whereas the Prophet ſaith: To day if ye will heare his voice, <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.</note> harden not your hearts.</p>
               <p>The fourth is perplexitie, vnſtayedneſſe, and trouble of mind, like vnto <hi>Saule,</hi> which after he had put away the Sorcerers and <note place="margin">1. Sam. 28.</note> Soothſayers out of the Land: yet when he was terrified by the armie of the Philiſtines, ſeeing it to be very great, and could haue no anſwere from God, neither by dreames, nor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim,</hi> nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, asked counſell of a Witch at <hi>Endor:</hi> So diuers which haue renounced that religion, and imbraced ours, yet lying at the point of death, in the midſt of their conflicts and tentations, thinking vpon the arguments which are brought on each ſide, and fearing to halt betweene two opinions, and ſo die vnreſolued; becauſe they haue not had at that inſtant conference with ſuch as were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> to reſolue them of all their doubts, haue ſuddenly reuolted, and not onely followed the example of <hi>Lots</hi> wife, which looked backe vnto <hi>Sodome,</hi> but alſo of the people which haue ſaide, come let vs goe backe into <hi>Aegipt</hi> againe.</p>
               <p>The fift is pride, and their owne inſolencie, whereby they are puffed vp, and thinke that all men muſt be ſubiect vnto them, <note place="margin">Num. 14.</note> but they neede ſubmit themſelues vnto none. As <hi>Bernardinus Ochinus</hi> writ a Booke in defence of Poligamie, affirming that <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſum coniugium,</hi> multitude of wiues was lawfull: ſuppoſing that after his Maiſter <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> was dead, no man was able to match him in writing or in diſputation: like <hi>Golias</hi> of <hi>Gath,</hi> which <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177853:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> challenged all commers to the combat. And this is the ſpeciall cauſe why Popes and generall Councels doe erre, becauſe they hold it as a principle in their Diuinitie that they cannot erre. For what doctrine will they bee afraide to publiſh, which are thus perſwaded of themſelues? Nay, who fals ſo ſoone as they which thinke their footing to be ſo faſt that they cannot fall? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle giueth this aduice: <hi>Qui videtur ſibi ſtare, videat ne cadat,</hi> He that thinketh that he ſtandeth, let him take heede <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> leſt he fall.</p>
               <p>The ſixt is ſingularitie: They will holde their opinions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will diſcent from vs, as if it were impoſſible that they and we ſhould agree together in one truth. They thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> and vs to bee <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> as if that Bath <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. li. 3. ca. 23. Iohn 4.</note> could not be wholeſome where <hi>Cerinthus</hi> doth waſh himſelfe; themſelues to be Iewes, and vs to be Samaritans, as if it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for them to drinke water out of our bucket which we doe draw; as if they would not haue any place in the Kingdome of heauen, but relinquiſh all their right and inheritance there, if they did thinke we ſhould come thither. Euen as ſome in our Church, although otherwiſe graue and learned, yet refuſe ſome good and wholeſome lawes and orders, becauſe they were, as they thinke, deuiſed by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is not a ſufficient Argument, that becauſe we hold it, therefore the doctrine ſhould be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, as it is no good conſequent, that becauſe they hold it, it ſhould be ſound, and orthodoxall. So then what is their proofe, but a womans reaſon, it is ſo, becauſe it is ſo; I will haue it ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I thinke ſo:
<q>
                     <l>Non amo te Voluci, non poſſum dicere quare,</l>
                     <l>Hoc tantum poſſum dicere, non amo te.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeuenth is inordinate affection, and loue of themſelues, for ſome will make their conſcience incline to their owne wil and affections, and not frame their deſires according to conſcience. For example, they thinke that religion ſoundeſt, which doeth moſt of all ſerue their turne, as the King <hi>Achab</hi> iudged thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <note place="margin">1. Reg. 22</note> to be beſt which preached pleaſing thing; but concerning <hi>Micheas,</hi> which prophecied other things then the King would haue him to prophecie, it was ſaid: Put this man in priſon, feede him with the bread of affliction, and water of affliction.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177853:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> So, becauſe of their corrupt and fleſhly nature they doe incline to libertie, they thinke that religion moſt probable which doeth fauour their affections moſt; that is, which holdeth ſimple for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication to be no ſinne, that offences may be redeemed by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that ordinarie faults which they commit, are not <hi>peccata,</hi> but <hi>peccadilia,</hi> not ſinnes, but trifles, which are eaſily pardoned and diſpenſed withall.</p>
               <p>The laſt is puſillanimitie, or weakeneſſe of minde, when they feare that which in ſincere iudgement they ought not to feare, as namely the diſlike of their friendes, the rebuke of their enemies, the voyce of the people, the good or bad report of other men, who will obiect apoſtaſie againſt them. So Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> though he knew Chriſt, yet ſaid he knew not the man, for feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke. <note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> And <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> although conuerted to be a Chriſtian, yet kept his place and profeſſion among the Phariſes ſtill, leaſt it ſhould be ſaid vnto him as afterward it was in the Goſpel: Art <note place="margin">Iohn. 7. Iohn 11.</note> thou alſo of <hi>Galile?</hi> Some relie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the opinion of great Doctors, whoſe iudgement they would, in modeſtie preferre before their owne, and in reſpect of them, ſomewhat diſtruſt themſelues, though they ſee euident demonſtrations to perſwade them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. As the Iewes would not beleeue in Chriſt, for feare of the Phariſes, although they ſaw a manifeſt ſigne, <hi>Lazarus</hi> raiſed from dead. They feare leaſt it ſhould be vpbraided vnto them as it was in the Goſpel: Doe any of the Rulers beleeue in him, but onely this people which know not the Law and are accurſed? As Cardinall <hi>Pole</hi> in his death-bed, ſaid, the proteſtants are the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der men, I would be a proteſtant were it not for the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> whereas they ſhould not ſo much reſpect the opinion of this Doctour or that Rabbi, when they ſee the plaine and open way lie before them, but preferre a manifeſt trueth aboue all. Therefore it behooueth our Countreymen to informe their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences better, and not to lay it vpon their conſcience that they liue diſorderly, and diſobedient to Chriſtian lawes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Hereſie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey lay hereſie to our charge, as if ſo be that we were like <note place="margin">Vide Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. Mart in tract. de. Sciſm.</note> to <hi>Seruerus, Cerinthus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Arrius.</hi> If we be heretiks, they do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177853:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> well to refraine our companie. But that we may the better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this argument, for the purgation of our ſelues, let vs firſt define what hereſie is. Secondly, let vs inquire by what Court or Conſiſtory we are condemned of hereſie. Thirdly, let vs ſet downe the fundamentall points of our Doctrine, that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare whether we were iuſtly condemned or no? Which being done, we ſhall not onely cleare our ſelues from iuſt ſuſpition of hereſie, but alſo demonſtrate how the greateſt Papiſts in the world, for learning and iudgement, do imbrace the ſame, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in them, with vs, not as if we did comforme our ſelues vnto them, becauſe wee holde the ſame concluſions which we haue alwayes held, but they ſeeing their owne errours laide open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and being in their owne conſciences conicted by a manifeſt trueth, do dayly; ſo farre as they dare, and may without the generall notice of the world, come neerer vnto vs, as if our doctrine in their knowledge were the ſoundeſt. And therefore, why ſhould not the inferiour ſorte of Catholikes which are but their diſciples doe the like? The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> being taxed by <hi>Luther</hi> for their diſcipline as looſe, and their doctrine as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, called the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> to deuiſe a reformation, ſeeing that in the eyes of the world they were not ſlandered. In that counſel they ſet foorth ſuch wholeſome Canons concerning Diſcipline as were fit for a reformed Church, but they were not ſo carefull of their points of Doctrine, becauſe they ſaw the world could ſooner looke into their diſorders, then iudge of their doctrine, and ſo did as it were yeeld <hi>Luthers</hi> complaint in parte to be iuſt. As for the doctrine, although they hold in termes the ſame which they did before, becauſe Princes and eſtates ſhould not thinke they had ſo long deceiued the world, and continued in error, and not eſpied the ſame vntill by <hi>Luther</hi> they had bin diſcouered, and as it were by him awaked like men which were in a dreame ſo many yeeres: yet they ſet downe their concluſions ſo cunningly, as if they would beare men in hand that they were (in ſome ſort) but miſtaken, &amp; inclined of themſelues ſomewhat vnto that which <hi>Luther</hi> perſwaded. Whereupon, ſome prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſuſpected that they had an intent, in time, to become Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, onely it ſhould come of themſelues, and not by force of <hi>Luthers</hi> arguments, vntill <hi>Andradius,</hi> a man more audacious then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177853:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the reſt, to remoue that hope of theirs, when he thought the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans to be more cold, and the brunt almoſt paſſed ouer, tooke vpon him to expound the meaning of the <hi>Tridentine</hi> counſell, and to conſter all points to as groſſe ſenſe as they were euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But nowe they beginne to incline to vs againe, inſomuch that Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> late Diuinitie Reader of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the learnedeſt Diuine of that Church which now liueth, in the courſe of his controuerſie lectures, though where he deliuereth the ſtate of the queſtion he bringeth what may be brought on their ſide, for faſhion ſake, that he may auoide all ſuſpition of hereſie with them: yet he handleth his matters ſo cunningly, and ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that in his concluſions he agreeth with vs in many things, although in diuers termes, wherein his predeceſſors vtterly diſſented from vs. And in many things he ſheweth himſelfe to be; ſo farre as he dareth, a Proteſtant, or at the leaſt not a Papiſt: if we take papiſtrie to be that which before it was. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth obſerue him well, ſhal finde how he diſcourſeth of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things ſuperfluous, like one which is more deſirous to deceiue the time, to fill vp the page with varietie of reading multitudes of Fathers, and citations of places, then to refute vs. Yet his Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes are allowed by the Inquiſition, and he is rewarded for his learned workes. Therefore I ſay, papiſtrie is newely corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and refined, they hold the ſame concluſions in generall termes which they did, but they hold them not as they did: they ſeeke out new defences, as if they could not ſtand to the olde, &amp; come neerer to vs in iudgement euery day. For ſo it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God in this latter end of the world to lighten their darkneſſe, and to quicken the dulneſſe of their vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>Touching the firſt, if they will vnderſtand what hereſie is, they muſt diſtinguiſh betweene hereſie and errour, for euery he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie is an error, but euery error is not an hereſie. As there is one error in maners, and ſo euery haynous offence is called a crime, as the adulterie of <hi>Dauid;</hi> but ſuch offences as are committed only vpon infirmitie, are cald by the general name of errors; ſo there is another error in doctrine, and euery man which holdeth a wrong opinion is ſaid to erre, as the Apoſtle did, which ſuppoſed the Kingdome of Chriſt to be of this world, and that the Goſpel was <note place="margin">Actes 1. Acts 11.</note> not to be publiſhed to the Gentiles: and theſe errors were no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177853:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> but that which is hereſie, is more dangerous and of an higher nature. It is an old ſaying: <hi>Errare poſſum, hereticus eſſe nolo,</hi> I may eaſily erre, as all men haue done, but an heretike I will not be.</p>
               <p>I define an hereſie in this maner: It is an error ſtifly and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately defended and maintained, not by a conſequent, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly impugning ſome Article of faith. For example, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note place="margin">Act. 15</note> erred when they helde it neceſſarie to be circumciſed, yet were not heretikes, becauſe they were not obſtinate; for they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues to the iudgement of the Church, and after due conſultation was had, they conſented to the truth. Againe, that opinion, did not directly impugne faith, but onely by a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle: Behold, I <hi>Paul</hi> ſay vnto you, if <note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> you be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing, for I teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie againe to euery one which is circumciſed, that he is bound to keepe the whole Law. Then, if we allow of Circumciſion, wee hold the Ceremoniall Law to be ſtill in force, and by a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent deny the death of Chriſt, by whoſe death onely that Law was aboliſhed. But <hi>Arrius</hi> was condemned for an heretike in the councell of <hi>Nice</hi> for theſe two cauſes: Firſt, he defended his error obſtinately, vntill his bellie burſt, and bowels guſhed out, not yeelding to the learned Biſhops of the world, which conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him by manifeſt places of the ſcriptures. Secondly, hee denied the Godhead of Chriſt contrary to the article of the Creede, which hath; and I beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt his onely ſon: and the doctrine of ſaint <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſaith hee was mightily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <note place="margin">Rom. 1</note> to bee the Son of God by his reſurrection from the dead: and of ſaint <hi>Iohn,</hi> which ſaith, God was the word. It is one thing therefore to denie the faith directly, as to ſay, Chriſt hath not yet ſuffered; and another thing to denie it by a conſequent, as they which hold a neceſſitie of circumciſion. But as for vs, we neither hold any opinions obſtinately, becauſe we wil recant &amp; ſubſcribe to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if they can diſproue vs by the ſcriptures: Neither doe we impugne any article of faith, becauſe wee holde the Creed of the Apoſtles, of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which the Papiſts alſo do hold, and the ſame Bible which we receiued from them, and we expound all theſe as all godly and learned antiquitie hath expounded them before vs,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177853:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> and therefore wee are vniuſtly charged with hereſie.</p>
               <p>That I may come to the ſecond thing which I propoſed. No Church can be condemned and adiudged hereticall by any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate cenſure, but it muſt be publike. Therefore they alleage for our condemnation, the decrees of the councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> againſt the authoritie of which councell we take theſe iuſt exceptions: Firſt, they call it a generall councell, as if almoſt all the Diuines of the world had beene aſſembled there. Let vs therefore number how many were preſent. They reckon for the credit of that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell as preſent, ſixe Cardinalls, foure Legates, three Patriarkes, two and thirtie Archbiſhops, two hundred twentie eight Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and fiue Abbats. Wee denie not, but at the end of the councel ſo many were procured to be there, but at the beginning, when matters were propounded, at the time when points of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were argued and debated, they exceeded not the number of fortie Biſhoppes, foure Legates; very ſmall aſſembly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the name of a generall councell, to conſider of ſo many weightie cauſes. Onely therefore at the latter end, the Pope ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt all Biſhops to forbeare comming thither, did create new Biſhops to make vp a number, and grace the councell with their preſence, and to ſubſcribe to all concluſions for forme ſake, which they did, neither here argued by others, nor yet well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of their ſelues. Therefore let indifferencie be the Iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and vs, whether ſo raſh a cenſure was to ſtand in force Secondly, who were there? onely our aduerſaries which <note place="margin">Ioh. 7</note> were of a contrary religion, we were not preſent, ſo that they did not onely by vs, as the Phariſies did by our Sauiour, contrary to lawe contemne vs in our abſence and our cauſe being not heard, but alſo the ſame men were both our accuſers and our Iudges. If ye aske a reaſon why we were not there? had wee letters of ſafe conduct? either could we haue truſted to ſuch conduct if it had bin graunted? What if they ſhould haue falſified their promiſe made to vs, as they did to <hi>Iohn Huz</hi> in the councell of <hi>Conſtance?</hi> eſpecialy they holding ſuch a Principle, as they are not bound to keepe faith and fidelitie with an heretike. But ſuppoſe wee had beene preſent, wee ſhould haue ſtood for ciphers and not for a number, becauſe they were linked together in the ſame confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, to ſuffer nothing to paſſe which might be preiudiciall to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177853:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> defineth thoſe councels, <note place="margin">Tom. 1. contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. 4. cap. 4.</note> onely to be vniuerſall, where all Biſhops of the world either were or might be preſent, theſe be his words: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi adſunt aut adeſſe poſſunt omnes Epiſcopitotius orbis</hi> and in the next chapter he defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that councell onely to be lawfull which the Pope hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, and the catholikes generally haue receiued. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all could be preſent as I haue declared, neither haue the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of Catholikes yet receiued that councell with the decrees thereof, for they are refuſed by the Catholikes of <hi>Germanie, France, Hungary, Bohemy, Poland,</hi> as our owne experience can tell vs.</p>
               <p>In the third place, foraſmuch as I haue ſhewed you, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians dwelling in one place are to meete together for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their religion, which conſiſteth in theſe three things pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the word, and the Sacraments: Let vs examine the worde which we teach, the leiturgie or forme of prayers which we vſe, the maner of our adminiſtration of the ſacraments whereof wee would that they ſhould be partakers.</p>
               <p>Concerning the doctrine, as I ſaide before, wee holde with them the ſame Creede, and the ſame Bible, concerning which Bible theſe haue bin the chiefeſt differences betweene them and vs, which follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt, whether all the books of the Bible be canonicall or no? They affirme that <hi>Tobie, Baruch, Iudith, Eccleſiaſticus, Wiſdome,</hi> the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and the fragment of <hi>Eſther &amp;c:</hi> be canonicall; we holde them for <hi>Apocripha.</hi> They prooue them to be cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall out of Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> we, that they be <hi>Apocripha</hi> out of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> both which doctors are of no ſmall authoritie with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore in this wee differ no more from them than Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> did from Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which did both agree, and were eaſily reconciled. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> meaning, that they were canonicall enough to prooue rules of life, not groundes of doctrine and faith. Thus Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> anſwered Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the Primitiue Church, thus we haue anſwered the Papiſts of our age: and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſince this anſwere was giuen, handling this controuerſie at large, replieth not againſt our anſwer. Onely he prooueth in generall termes, that they be canonical, which we do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177853:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo confeſſe, but hee dooth not ſo much as mention this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Cannons of faith, and Cannons of good life and manners, much leſſe dooth hee reply againſt it, therefore wee take it <hi>proconceſſo,</hi> as a thing graunted by the Lawes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 1. capitibus 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> that hee holdeth as wee holde, fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth to our defence, and ſo reſteth ſatisfied with our anſwer, and the caſe to be cleere betweene vs both.</p>
               <p>Secondly: A queſtion hath beene debated betweene vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Bible, foraſmuch as there be many editions, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue, Greeke, Latine, which is the beſt? Wee ſay the Hebrew, they the Latine, and the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> hath obtruded to vs one only Latine edition, that is, the old vulgare tranſlation, and decreed, that it onely ſhould be authenticall and no other, that all others ſhould be corrected by it, and it by none. Wee grant it fit, that for vniformitie in quotations of places in ſchools and pulpits, one Latine text ſhould be vſed, and we can be contented, for the antiquitie thereof, to preferre that before all other Latine books, ſo much we do yeeld to the Councell: But foraſmuch as that tranſlation hath many faults, as al other tranſlations haue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the workes of men, we preferre the originall, that is, the olde Teſtament in the Hebrew, and the new in Greeke farre before it, foraſmuch as they were written by the finger of God the Holy Ghoſt, which cannot erre. And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendeth to our opinion, as more ſound than the decree of the councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſhewing that whereſoeuer the Latine bookes do diſcent one from another, that it may be diſcerned, which is the trueſt, each of them to be examined by the originall, which is of greater authoritie, and the Latine bookes to be corrected by them, that onely to be ſound, which agreeth with them, and that to be reiected, which diſcenteth from them. His words are theſe: <hi>Ad aliud de emendatione Latinorum codicum ad Hebraeos</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 2. cap. 11</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; Graecos respondeo, quatuor temporibus licere nobis recurrere al fontes Hebraeos &amp; Graecos, vt illi patres monent. Primo quando in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris codicibus videtur eſſe error librariorum &amp;c: Secundo, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Latini codices variant, vt non poſſit certò ſtatus quae ſit vera vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata Lectio, poſſumus ad fontes recurrere, &amp; inde iuuari ad veram Lectionem inueniendam. Sic Ioſue 5. quidam Latini codices habent: Quibus iurauit vt ostenderet illis terram lecte fluentem &amp; molle,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:177853:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>quidam habent, vt non ostenderet &amp;c: vera lectio videtur eſſe poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. Nam in Hebraeo constantèr additur, Non. Sicut è contrariò Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue 11. Quidam codices habent: Non fuit ciuitas quae non ſe trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret: Quidam habent: Non fuit ciuitas quae ſe traderet, Et hoc eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius quià conforme eſt Hebraeo, &amp; verba ſequentia id requirunt. Sic Lucae 1. quidem codices habent: Redemptionem plebiſuae: Quidam plebi ſuae, &amp; haec videtur verior, cùm in Graeco ſit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>A third queſtion concerning the Bible is, whether all grounds of ſaluation, all things which are abſolutely neceſſarie for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man to know, be contained in the corpes and body of the Bible? They haue held, in times paſt, that the Bible was inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <note place="margin">Vide Concil. Trident.</note> and therefore they added vnto it traditions, which they call vnwritten verities, and would haue them to be of as great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie as the ſcriptures; as neceſſary to bee beleeued and obayed. but now, <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as if he were aſhamed of that aſcertion, doth relinquiſh it, and after he hath ſpoken in the defence of traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons what he can, concludeth that all things which are neceſſary, are contained in the Apoſtles. His wordes are theſe: <hi>Primum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 4. cap. 10</note> 
                  <hi>est, quaedam in doctrinâ Christianâ tam fides quam morum eſſe ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer omnibus neceſſaria, ad ſalutem, qualis est notitia; articulorum Symboli Apoſtolici, item congnitio decem praeceptorum, &amp; nonnul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ſacramentorum. Cetera non ita neceſſaria ſunt, vt ſine eorum explicatâ notitiâ, &amp; fide &amp; profeſſione ſaluari homo non poſſit, modo promptam habeat voluntatem ea ſuſcipiendi &amp; credendi, quando ſibi fuerint legitimè per Eccleſiam propoſita &amp;c: His notatis, dico, illa omnia ſcripta eſſe ab Apoſtolis, quae ſunt omnibus neceſſaria, &amp; quae ipſi palàm omnibus vulgo praedicauerant: alia autem non omnia ſcripta eſſe.</hi> But whatſoeuer they can prooue out of the Bible, we will receiue; as for things which are not neceſſarie, although we diſcent concerning them, they ought not therefore to refuſe to communicate with vs.</p>
               <p>A fourth queſtion is, of the authoritie of the ſcriptures, and who ought of right to be iudge of the ſame. They were wont to hold the Church, that is, the generall Councell, to be aboue the ſcriptures, and the vndoubted Iudge of the ſame; we the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie. Now <hi>Bellarmine</hi> condeſcendeth vnto vs, that the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church ſpecified in the councel of <hi>Trent</hi> may ſo farre <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 3. cap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> be ſubiect to the ſcriptures, as to be examined by the ſcriptures,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177853:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and that the authority of the Church is inferior to the authority of the ſcriptures. His words are theſe: <hi>Addo etiam, quod etſi haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus peccat dubitando de auctoritate Eccleſiae, in quam per Baptiſmum regeneratus est, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt eadem conditio haeretici qui ſemel fidem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſus eſt, &amp; Iudaei aut Ethnici, qui nunquam fuit Christianus: tamen, poſito hoc dubio, &amp; hoc peccato, non male facit ſcrutando &amp; exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando, an loca ſcripturae &amp; Patrum à concilio Tridentino prelata ita ſehabeant, modo id faciat intentione inueniendi veritatem non ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnian di. Deberet quidem ille ſine examine recipere doctrinam Eccleſiae, tamen melius est vt examinando praeparetur adveritatem, quam negligendo remaneat in ſuis tenebris.</hi> And againe in the ſame Chapter. <hi>Decimum quartum argumentum: Si Pontifex indicat de ſcripturis, ſequitur Pontificem ſeu concilium eſſe ſupra ſcripturam: &amp; ſi ſcripturae ſenſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſine Pontifice ſeu concilio non est authenticus, ſequitur verbum Dei accipere robur &amp; firmitatem à verbo Hominum. Respondeo hoc argumentum quod ab haereticis plurimi fit, totum in aequiuocatione verſari: Nam duobus modis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt intelligi Eccleſiam iudicare de ſcripturis: vno modo quod iudicat, verúmne ſit an falſum quod ſcripturae docent: altero modo, quod poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vt fundamento certiſſimo ſcripturae verba eſſe veriſſima, iudicet quae ſit vera eorum interpretatio. Et quidem, ſi primo modo Eccleſia iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caret, verè eſſet ſupra ſcripturam, ſed hoc non dicimus, quamuis hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici calumnientur id nos dicere, qui paſſim vociferantur nos ſubij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſcripturam pedibus Papae. At ſecundo modo iudicare Eccleſiam vel Pontificem de ſcripturis, quod nos aſſerimus, non eſt Eccleſiam eſſe ſupra ſcripturam, ſed ſupra iudicia priuatorum hominum. Non enim iudicat Eccleſia de veritate ſcripturae ſed de intelligentiâ tuâ &amp; meâ, &amp; aliorum, Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hinc ſumit verbum Dei aliquod robur, ſed intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia nostra. Non enim ſcriptura eſt verior aut certior, quia ſic ab Eccleſia exponitur, ſed mea ſententia est verior quando ab Eccleſia confirmatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I could goe almoſt through all the controuerſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and vs. But I doe content my ſelfe with the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points. Therefore I exhort them which hold vs for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, firſt, to reade diligently, to peruſe and examine their owne writers, and what they hold, to conferre their groundes with ours, and then to examine their owne iudgements, whether they finde vs heretikes or no. And as for thoſe matters, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177853:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> be no fundamentall poyntes, although in them wee diſcent, wee muſt not diſpaire of their conuerſion. For God neither hath nor will reueale vnto them all trueth at once, but, as the blind man in the Ghoſpell, when hee firſt beganne to ſee, thought hee ſawe <note place="margin">Marke. 8</note> men walking like trees, but when our Sauiour touched his eyes againe, he ſaw more clearely: So God will lighten the darkneſſe of their hearts, and take away the vaile or couering which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, by degrees, vntill they come to the full meaſure of knowledge, which the Holy Ghoſt ſhall iudge expedient to be reuealed vnto them.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Faith and Workes.</head>
                  <p>TO leaue theſe generall grounds, and to diſpute more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. They hold, with Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> that workes do iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie; <note place="margin">Iam. 2. Rom. 5.</note> we with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> iuſtification by Faith, and ſith theſe two Apoſtles differ in wordes, and not in meaning, why ſhould wee diſagree, holding the ſame which they doe hold? Faith goeth before, and workes follow after iuſtification, but both do iuſtifie: ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> argueth from that which is precedent, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> argueth from that which is ſubſequent, and both argue well. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Grammaticall ſignification of the word, as to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie ſignifieth, <hi>iuſtum facere,</hi> to make a man iuſt: ſo neither faith nor yet workes do iuſtifie, but God alone, according to the acception which is vſed in Law, as to iuſtifie ſignifieth, <hi>iuſtum declarare,</hi> to abſolue a man and pronounce him iuſt out of the mouth of a iury or a Iudge, ſo faith which is inuiſible iuſtifieth vs before the inuiſible god, which ſeeth our inviſible faith, &amp; works which are viſible, iuſtifie vs before viſible men, which ſee our workes as they be viſible and ſenſible things. As the Angels when they came vnto <hi>Lot,</hi> had not beene intertained, had they not cloathed themſelues with bodily ſhapes, ſo men cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our faith vnleſſe it be as it were cloathed and beautified with workes. But to ſpeake of that which is worſt: They hold <note place="margin">Gen. 19</note> that workes are meritorious, and therefore they worke that they may merit heauen, we aſcribing leſſe vnto our ſelues, and more vnto God, thinke not ſo honourably of our workes, and yet wee thinke workes as neceſſary as they doe, and therefore wee will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177853:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> worke, and we will worke, that we may be ſaued, and wee will worke out our ſaluation with feare and trembling. Wee holde workes neceſſarie for them which will inherit, but not for them which will merit, and therefore we worke not that wee may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> yet that we may inherite, and our workes haue theſe foure ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vſes, that by them we may glorifie God, benefite our neighbour, exerciſe our faith, and make our election ſure. For with vs this is the very definition of a worke: An action of the regenerate according to the Law of God, done to theſe ends, that God, by it may be glorified, our neighbor profited, our faith exerciſed, and our election confirmed. And although wee worke not for that end as they do, yet becauſe without workes we muſt not thinke to pleaſe God, wee will worke as much as they doe, and the ſame workes which they doe, with the ſame zeale which they doe, which thinke to merit. Wee will worke as earneſtly as if we thought to merit, and yet we wilbe farre off from thinking that we merit, becauſe when we haue done all that <note place="margin">Luc. 17</note> we are commaunded to doe, wee are but vnprofitable ſeruants, and therefore we will relie vpon the merits of Chriſt alone, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing our ſelues and our workes. Let them iudge then who are ſafeſt, they or we. Our difference is not concerning the worke it ſelfe, but only concerning the opinion which we ought to conceiue of the worke, they thinke honourably, wee baſely, of our owne workes, but worke the ſame. And certainely, the worthineſſe of workes doth not conſiſt in the excellent opinion which we conceiue of them, but in the true and faithfull work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not in the pleaſing of our ſelues with our ſelues, or any thing which procedeth from vs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Free will.</head>
                  <p>THis queſtion hath bred ſome difference betweene vs in the ſchooles, and yet if we do vnderſtand each other, we may be eaſily reconciled. For the ſcriptures ſpeake ſo plainely, that they take away doubts: We are, ſay they, not of our ſelues ſufficient to thinke a good thought, as of our ſelues, but all our ſufficiencie is of God. The way of man is not in himſelfe, neither is it in man <note place="margin">1. Corint. 3. Ierem. 10</note> to walke and direct his ſteps. No man commeth to Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177853:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Father draw him. Draw me, and wee will runne after <note place="margin">Iohn. 6 Cant. 1 Rom. 7</note> thee. What good I would doe, that doe I not, the euill which I would not doe, that doe I, ſaith the Apoſtle. To conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there are three ſorts of agents; the one working of his meere will and pleaſure, which is God; the other of neceſſitie, which is nature; a third betweene both theſe extreames, partly of willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and partely of neceſſitie, which is man. And as no man is good againſt his will, ſo no man hath power to will any thing that is good, vnleſſe God giueth him that will. So ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: It is God which worketh in you euen the wil and deede, <note place="margin">Phil. 2</note> of his owne good will and pleaſure. And this will may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the eye, which being in darkeneſſe, yet is not blinde, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth it ſee without the eſpeciall grace of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Prayer.</head>
                  <p>WE inuocate God alone, who we are ſure doth heare vs, and they confeſſe, that in ſo doing wee doe well, why then will they not ioyne with vs in well doing? But, as for Saints departed, when they pray to them, to be prayed for by them, they are not certaine that they doe heare them, becauſe it cannot be ſufficiently prooued; why then will they not pray with vs whoſe prayers they confeſſe to be voyde of exception? They denie not but that it is better to pray to God then to Saints, why then had they not rather be ſure of the firſt place, then doubt of the ſecond? Their prayer to Saints may breede a ſcruple in their conſcience, whether they do well or no. For, if they heare them not, their praiers are idle words, but they muſt anſwere at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Matth. 12.</note> for euery idle word which they ſhall ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>As we pray not to Saints departed, ſo wee pray not for Saints or any other deceaſed. If they be in heauen, they neede not our prayers, if in hel, no prayers can helpe them, and we dare not ſay they are in purgatory, ſith purgatory, by the confeſſion of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> is a tradition, &amp; not containd in the ſcriptures. He writes that there be many things neceſſary to be known, which are not contained in the ſcriptures, he doth reckon them vp in order, and he placeth them ſo; firſt, that women were purged from ſinne,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177853:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> though vncircumciſed: ſecondly, that children that died before the eight day, were alſo purged from originall ſinne: thirdly, many Gentiles in the old teſtament were ſaued: fourthly, that of neceſſitie there be ſome books which are the holy ſcriptures: fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it muſt be knowne which bookes are the holy ſcriptures: ſixtly, that the bookes which wee haue in our hands are the holy ſcriptures: ſeauenthly, that the ſcriptures are to be vnderſtood: eightly, that <hi>Mary</hi> was a perpetuall Virgine: ninthly, that Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is to be celebrated on the Lordes day: tenthly, that Infants are to be baptized: eleuenthly, purgatory: But marke his words, he ſaith, many things are neceſſary to be knowne, which are not contained in the ſcriptures, among thoſe he maketh pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to be the eleuenth, therefore he affirmeth, that purgatory is a thing neceſſary to be knowne, and not in the ſcriptures, and yet as a man that would halte betweene two religions, to pleaſe vs, and not diſpleaſe the Papiſts, doth lay it vpon <hi>Luther,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Credit Lutherus purgatorium eſſe, &amp; tamen aſſerit purgatorium non poſſe probari in ſacris literis. Luther</hi> ſaith, he belieueth that there is a purgatory, and yet ſaith, it cannot be prooued out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The queſtion is, whether <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth not ſay ſo as well as <hi>Luther.</hi> If he do not: firſt, why doth he not expreſſe his owne minde to the contrary in that place? ſecondly, why doth he in that long catalogue of ſuch things as are not contained in the ſcriptures reckon purgatory to be the eleuenth? He ſheweth that the tenth tradition or vnwritten veritie is the baptiſme of Infants, that <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> hold it lawefull, and yet his ſelfe doth not refuſe that opinion which they doe hold, and the like muſt be vnderſtood concerning purgatory, that as <hi>Luther</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth purgatory to be contained in the ſcriptures, ſo doth <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> or elſe he doth contradict himſelfe, which ſaid before that <hi>Pargatorium eſt vndecimum eorum quae ignorari non poſſunt, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in ſcripturis non continentur,</hi> Purgatory is the eleuenth of theſe things, whereof we may not be ignorant, and yet are not contained in the ſcriptures. Sith therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> repeating many things which are not contained in the ſcripture, of which one to be purgatory, and yet before as I haue ſhewd, granteth all things to be contained in the ſcriptures which are neceſſary for our ſaluation, that we ſhould know them, ye muſt beare with vs <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 2. cap. 11.</note>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177853:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> if we doe not belieue purgatorie, being no matter of ſaluation to vs to belieue it.</p>
                  <p>We pray in our mother tongue, what exception doe they take againſt it? Their priuate prayers are in Engliſh, as it appeareth by their Ieſus pſalter, their Manuall of Meditations, and ſundry other prayer books which they haue printed, I would know why it might not be as lawfull to pray publikely in the ſame tongue. Which is more, I haue ſeene the Maſſe, by them ſet forth in Spaniſh, the Spaniſh being in one page of the booke, and the Latine in the other. In times paſt, the Engliſh teſtament was printed with the Engliſh in one page, and the Latine in the other, and licenſed to be printed, and publikely ſold by King <hi>Philip</hi> and Qu. <hi>Mary.</hi> And now of late our Engliſh Seminaries of <hi>Rhemes</hi> haue publiſhed the New Teſtament in Engliſh, with promiſe alſo to ſet forth the old, why may not the Engliſh Bible be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by vs as well as by the Seminaries, and as well be read pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in our Church as in their houſes? But to come to the point, <note place="margin">See Greg. Mart. his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face at large concerning the Scriptures in Engliſh.</note> 
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth thoſe prayers which are in a knowne tong to be beter then thoſe which are not vnderſtood, why then ſhould not that which is inferiour giue place vnto that which is better? God is beſt pleaſed when he is beſt ſerued, and he is beſt ſerued where he is prayed vnto after the beſt maner. <hi>Bellarmines</hi> words are theſe: <hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> his repugnant ſcripturae illae: populus hic labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is me honorat, &amp;c: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orem linguâ, ſpiritus meus erat, me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s autem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè fructu eſt: In poſteriore ſcripturâ, non reprehenditur oratio quae non intelligitur ſed ei anteponitur oratio quae intelligitur.</hi> In the ſame chapter hee confeſſeth that the Pope gaue licence to the whole <note place="margin">De verbo Dei lib. 2. cap. 16</note> land of <hi>Morauia,</hi> to haue their publike ſeruice in their owne tongue, why ſhould hee denie the ſame to vs? I doubt not but hee woulde diſpenſe with vs, if wee woulde take ſuch a diſpenſation from him. If it be of it ſelfe euill, his diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot make it good, and if it be of it ſelfe good, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods word, it needeth not to be ſtrengthned by his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. As he cannot diſpenſe againſt Gods word, ſo Gods word of it ſelfe is warranted without mans diſpenſation.</p>
                  <p>They obiect, that vntil of late through the Weſt parte of the world publike prayers were in Latine, in the Eſt part in Greeke, euen among thoſe nations to whom theſe languages were no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177853:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> tongues. I anſwere, that when theſe nations were firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, they were ſubiect to the Romane Emperour, which ſpake Latine as his mother tongue, and therefore all endeuoured to ſpeake as the Emperour ſpake, although it were but broken Latine, and therefore receiued their Leiturgie in Latine. (And as for the Eaſt they ſpake Greeke, as commonly as the reſt did ſpeake Latine) ſo in <hi>Wales</hi> their mother tongue is Welch, in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> Corniſh, In <hi>Ireland</hi> Iriſh, yet in all theſe places the publike ſeruice is read in Engliſh, and the people haue applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſpeake Engliſh, becauſe they are ſubiects to the King of <hi>England.</hi> But now the Weaſt part of the world, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Latine Church, is not ſubiect to any man that ſpeaketh Latine as his proper language, and the Latine tong hath ceaſed to be familiar among the people, wherefore then ſhould not their ſeruice be now in the tongue which they vnderſtand, as in the beginning it was in the Latine which they then vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood? Godly diſcretion would thinke it fitte, now we haue the benefite of printing, which in the old time we had not, and wee haue ſuch meanes to aduance religion, as our forefathers had not, that euery people ſhould haue their Leiturgie, not onely in that tongue which they doe vnderſtand, as then it was, but alſo in that tongue which they doe naturally ſpeake and beſt vnderſtand, as nowe all reformed Churches almoſt haue. And this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration mooued the reuerend Father, Doctour <hi>Morgan,</hi> now Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Saint <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and Doctour <hi>Goodman,</hi> the late Deane of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to take paines for the tranſlating and publiſhing of the Bible in the Welch tong, by which their trauailes and godly indeuours they haue aduanced the Ghoſpel in their owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And his Highneſſe ſhal truly performe the office of a King, if he take order that all men, women, and children, may be brought to ſpeake Engliſh, or elſe, that they may haue the lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie tranſlated, and printed in the Iriſh tongue.</p>
                  <p>It hath bin obiected in the defence of Latin ſeruice, that it is profitable for them vvhich vnderſtand it not, becauſe, ſay they, publike praiers are not made to the people, but to god which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth, in the behalfe of the people which vnderſtand not. Euen as if an Aduocate ſhould pleade before a Iudge which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth, for his Client which is not able to vnderſtand the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177853:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtate of his owne cauſe and buſines, and yet is as effectually hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Aduocate, as if the Client did vnderſtand I anſwere, that it is enough if the Aduocate vnderſtand which pleadeth, becauſe the Aduocate pleadeth alone, but if the Client ſhould ioyne in plea with the Aduocate, it were neceſſary alſo that the Client ſhould vnderſtand, becauſe without vnderſtanding hee could not pleade, and ſpeake for himſelfe. But our pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are ordained to this end, that not onely learned men ſhould reſorte thither, as in Schooles and Colleges, which doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Latine, but all ignorant people, for the ſanctifying of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, and exerciſe of their religion, that not onely the miniſters there ſhould pray for them, as the Aduocate alone ſpeaketh for his Client, but they alſo ſhould pray for their owne ſelues; and this is the difference betweene the courtes of earthly Iudges and the court of heauen. The people come not to the Church onely to be prayed for by the Miniſter, for ſo they may ſtay at home in their owne houſes and be prayed for in the Church, but they come to pray themſelues, both for others and for themſelues, to ioyne with the miniſter in prayer, as the Apoſtle doth teach them ſaying: Now the God of patience and conſolation graunt that <note place="margin">Rom. 15</note> ye may be like minded one to another according to Chriſt Ieſus, that ye with one minde and one mouth may praiſe God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. But this they cannot doe vnleſſe they vnderſtand. He that prayeth and vnderſtandeth not his owne words, may thinke he prayeth when he ſweareth, and when he prayeth, he knoweth not that he prayeth, as the high prieſt prophecied, but knew not that he did prophecie, as the parret which laugheth, knoweth not that he laugheth, and the Thru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes <note place="margin">Iohn 11.</note> and black-birds ſing, but know not that they doe ſing. But becauſe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath compared praying vnto pleading, what kinde of plea ſhall that be, which neither Client nor Aduocate doth vnderſtand? It cannot be denied but in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, in many of our Churches the ſeruice was read, but not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ther of the people, nor yet the prieſt; and ſo it is now in ſome countries, where Sir <hi>Iohn Lacke latine</hi> hath the charge of ſoules, and vnderſtandeth not the Maſſe which he readeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alleadgeth out of <hi>Ezra,</hi> that he read the law before <note place="margin">2. Ezr. 8</note> the people, and prayed in a language which they vnderſtood not,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177853:16"/> and yet that the people did anſwer AMEN. He did reade, ſaith he, in a ſtrange language, that is, in the Hebrue, for he could not reade in the <hi>Chalde,</hi> becauſe that is a paraphraſe and no text, not in the <hi>Syriac,</hi> becauſe that tranſlation was not then extant, and as for the Hebrue, they vnderſtood it not, as appeareth by theſe arguments; firſt, from the ſtory, for after <hi>Eſdras</hi> had read, the Leuites came and interpreted, which had beene needeleſſe if they had vnderſtood it themſelues. The ſecond from obſeruation, For the Iewes, ſaith he, forgot their Hebrue tong being captiues ſeauentie yeares in <hi>Babel,</hi> and learned the language of the land where they dwelt which was <hi>Calde,</hi> and yet not able to ſpeake it naturally, they ſpake a third kinde of dialect which was the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac,</hi> conſiſting partly of the Hebrue, and partly of the Chalde, which language to them became their mother tongue, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the <hi>Syriac</hi> words in the ghoſpel, which are therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hebrue, becauſe at that time the Hebrues ſpake them. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere firſt to the ſtory out of the ſtory. The text hath: And <hi>Ezra</hi> the prieſt brought the law before the congregation both of men &amp; women, and of all that could heare and vnderſtand it. Againe, he read there in the ſtreete that was before the water gate, from the morning vntill midday, before men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and them that vnderſtood it. Therefore it is euident by the teſtimony of the holy ghoſt, that the people vnderſtood that language wherein the law was written and read vnto them. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> asketh what neede there was then of an expoſitour? I anſwere, the Leuites expounded not the words, but the ſenſe, for the text ſaith: The Leuites cauſed the people to vnderſtand the law, and in the next verſe is explained, how the people were cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to vnderſtand the law, not the words of the law, but the law it ſelfe, not the tongue wherein the law was written, but the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it, for ſo it followeth in the 8. verſe: And they read in the booke of the law of God diſtinctly, and gaue the ſenſe, and cauſed the people to vnderſtand the reading, that is, they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon it. And foraſmuch as the ſtory ſaith: they read di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, what neede was there of diſtinct reading to them which vnderſtood not the language?</p>
                  <p>I anſwere to his obſeruation. Foraſmuch as the <hi>Chalde</hi> and <hi>Syriac</hi> were but dialects of the Hebrew, as the <hi>Doric</hi> and <hi>Ionic</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177853:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> are but Dialects of the Greeke, and the Scottiſh tongue is a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the Engliſh: it was incredible that the Iewes in their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, hauing among them Prophets and zealous Prieſts, their ſelues being alſo zealous, and fully aſſured to returne againe, ſhould ſo forget their tongue, as not to vnderſtand their owne Bible, ſo well as the <hi>Dorics</hi> vnderſtand common Greeke, and the Scottiſh men do vnderſtand Engliſh. But which is more, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the manner of the Iewes euer hath bin when they were dwelling in ſtrange places, to ſpeake the language of the place where they dwelt, as I know by my owne experience the Iewes at <hi>Frankefort</hi> ſpeake Dutch, of <hi>Prage Bohemiſh &amp;c:</hi> which tongues haue no affinitie with the Hebrew, yet in all places their ſeruice is in Hebrew, and their cuſtome as it hath beene, ſo ſtill continueth, to teach their Children ſo much Hebrew, as may be ſufficient to vnderſtand the Bible, and it is manifeſt by the ſtorie that the Iewes in <hi>Babylon</hi> did the like.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all. Concerning our prayers, if they do vvell looke ouer their ovvne miſſall or Maſſe-booke vvhich vvas vſed in <hi>England</hi> according to the cuſtome of <hi>Sarum,</hi> and conferre it with our Seruice booke, they ſhall finde that there are few things in it, but they are either taken out of the Bible, or which vvas good, in that miſſal, ſo that they cannot eaſily miſlike our ſeruice book, vnleſſe they vvill condemne a beſt parte of their ovvne Maſſe-Booke and the Bible. So then, they may ſafely come to our Church, vve cannot vvithout violating our conſcience come to theirs, our prayers are in Engliſh which all they vnderſtand, their prayers are in Latin which our people vnderſtand not; they pray for the dead without warrant, we for the liuing, for the which they confeſſe wee haue warrant enough, they pray to the dead, which wee for iuſt cauſes diſallow, wee pray to the liuing one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I meane the liuing God, againſt which they take no excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Sacraments.</head>
                  <p>COncerning the number of Sacraments, we will not diſpute, for as they define a Sacrament, there are more than ſeauen, as we define it, there are but two. This therefore ſhall not breed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177853:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> any ſuch iarre betweene vs, that therefore wee ſhould refuſe to communicate together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
                  <p>WEe hold them which are baptized in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be ſo ſufficiently baptized, that they may not be baptized againe; neither do they rebaptize them which haue bin baptized in our Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Lordes Supper.</head>
                  <p>AS often as we be made partakers of the Lordes Table, wee <note place="margin">1. Corint. 11</note> receiue the Lords body, becauſe he hath ſaide it his owne ſelfe. We receiue it with reuerence and deuotion, becauſe it is his body. For we muſt not, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, eate it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, leſt ſo we be guiltie of the Lords body, neither will we eate our owne damnation, for not diſcerning the Lordes bodie. But how it is his body we cannot ſee by the eyes of our bodies, or humane reaſon, neither can they, onely wee diſcerne it by the eyes of faith, and ſo ought they to do. <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> and the learned of their Church were wont to ſay, it was his bodie <hi>ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili modo,</hi> after an vnſpeakable maner, after ſuch a maner as mens tongues could not vtter. And therefore, as the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Tiguri</hi> putteth them in minde, they ſeeme to haue forgotten what they ſaid before when they take vpon them to <hi>farimodum,</hi> that is, <note place="margin">Contrà testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Brentij.</note> to expreſſe in plaine terms of logicke, &amp; yet cleane contrary and repugnant to the rules of logicke, his body to be really, naturally, and ſubſtantially hidden and comprehended vnder the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bread. It is very ſtrange, both to expreſſe that which they ſay cannot be expreſſed, and that the accidents of bread, can haue their being, when the bread it ſelfe hath no being, in whoſe only being their eſſence and being doth conſiſt.</p>
                  <p>But be it as it is, no man can know more or ſooner than God wil reueale, what expoſitions ſoeuer the ſubtitle and varietie of mens wits do deuiſe; this ſacrament is in our Church adminiſtred by vs as it was by our Sauior Chriſt, and is ſet downe in the ſtory of the Goſpel. I would know therefore what exception they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177853:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> take againſt it, why they ſhould not receiue it with vs? It is no ſcruple or barre to their conſciences in what ſence we do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, ſo as we deliuer it vnto them according to the true man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme of our Sauiour Chriſt his inſtitution. And if they will ſubmit themſelues to the lawes of our Church, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it at our handes, we will not be ouer-haſtie with them to examine them how they doe expound the wordes, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum:</hi> This is my bodie. For we know they cannot eate it but by faith, and ſo we wil leaue them to Gods mercy, that he would vouchſafe in good time further to ſatisfie them, lay open, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale his truth vnto them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Sciſme.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THey alleadge we are Sciſmatikes, becauſe we haue made a defection from the Catholike Church, and withdrawne our neckes out of the yoake of obedience to the head of the Church which is the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that being ſeperated from the head, we cannot be liuing members of that myſticall body. My anſwere is: The head of the Church is Chriſt, <note place="margin">1. Cor, 11.</note> and we as members are conglutinate and ioyned vnto that head, and to them which obiect that our Sauior Chriſt in his abſence muſt haue his Deputie, that the Deputy or Vicar generall of Chriſt is the Holy-Ghoſt, which hath the gouernement of the Church. Euen as <hi>Elias</hi> aſcending vp let his mantle downe vpon <hi>Eliſeus,</hi> to be with him in his ſteade: ſo our Sauiour departing <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2 Act. 2 Matth. 28. Act. 20.</note> from vs ſent downe the Holy-Ghoſt to poſſeſſe his roome, and to abide with vs vntill the end of the world: Take heede, ſaieth the Apoſtle, to your ſelues, and to all the flocke whereof the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-ghoſt hath made you ouer-ſeers; ſo then the Holy-Ghoſt hath the gouernement of the Church. But, ſay they, a viſible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy muſt haue a viſible head proportionably to the body, and therefore ſome one man muſt be ouer the Church. I deny not but weake men deſire a viſible obiect ſtill before their eies, as the Iſraelites when <hi>Moſes</hi> was out of their ſight but a few dayes, <note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> would make a calfe to be their gouernour, rather than they would want one to be viſibly reſident among them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Sauior, becauſe we ſhould not in his abſence committe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177853:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> the like idolatry, did leaue the viſible Sacrament of the Euchariſt among vs ſaying: This is my body. But yet I do anſwer that a ſimilitude muſt not, as the Schoolemen ſay, <hi>Currere quatuor pedibus:</hi> agree in all things. Firſt therefore, it is not ſimply ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie that the viſible bodie ſhould ſtill haue a viſible head in ſight as if it could not ſtand without ſuch an head. For God had his Church viſible vpon the earth before the Papacie, and before the Incarnation of Chriſt, but Chriſt the head of the Church before his incarnation could not be a viſible head. So therefore, as Chriſt in his Godhead alone before hee was borne, was the head of his Church, though inuiſible, likewiſe is he now in his Godhead and Manhoode vnited together, head of the church viſible, although vpon the earth not to be ſeene. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the time hath beene when there was a long vacancie of the Popedome, by reaſon of ciuill diſſention, yet the Church then ſtood without ſuch an head. Thirdly, no ſinfull man is able to diſcharge ſuch an office as to be ouer-ſeer of the vniuerſal church. Fourthly, there muſt be ſuch an influence of neceſſitie from the head to the body, as cannot poſſibly be from any man to the Church. Fiftly, the Pope neuer was reputed as head of the whole Church; for the Eaſt part of the world, that is, the Greeke Church was euer ſo auerſe from the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> that it could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet be brought, either to obedience to the Pope, or to ioyne in rites and ceremonies with his Church, or to be incorporated into that body, or to vſe the ſame leiturgie and forme of prayer which that Church vſeth. All appellations amongſt them haue bin to the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as to the higheſt Biſhop. Sixtly, what authoritie ſoeuer the Pope hath had ouer the Latine Church and Weſt part of the world, it hath beene giuen him by humane conſtitutions onely, and generall conſent of Princes and States, which they ſuffered him to enioy, during their owne good liking, and no longer. And laſt of all, our owne experience can enforme vs, that the Catholike princes which are moſt of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted to the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> will be ſo farre ſubiect as they thinke fit, and no further. <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, late Emperor and King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> tooke priſoner, <hi>Clement</hi> the Pope, when hee reſiſted his proceedings in <hi>Italie,</hi> and Queene <hi>Mary</hi> made her Coſin <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Pole</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> though the Pope with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177853:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> it: neither doe the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> though of the Romiſh religion, euer ſuffer the Popes to beare any ſtroke in the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Biſhops. I wiſh therefore that they would be better aduiſed before they lay ſciſme vnto our charge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Diſcord, and Inconſtancie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe vſuall obiections againſt vs were wont to be, that wee haue ſects and diuiſions among vs. But ſo had they often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>Eckius</hi> againſt <hi>Pighius, Thomas</hi> againſt <hi>Scotus,</hi> ſo had the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> againſt <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſome were of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Cephas.</hi> We contend about white and blacke, round and ſquare, but in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, we agree. That concerning the booke of common prayer when the maſſe was firſt put downe, king <hi>Henry</hi> had his Engliſh Leiturgie, and that was iudged abſolute without exception, but when King <hi>Edward</hi> came to the Crowne, that was condemned, and other in the place which <hi>Peter</hi> Martyr, and <hi>Bucer</hi> did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue as very conſonant to Gods word. When Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> beganne hir raigne, the former was iudged to be full of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and a new was deuiſed, and allowed by the conſent of the Clergie. But about the middle of her raigne wee grew weary of that booke, and great meanes haue beene wrought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon that, and eſtabliſh an other, which although it was not obtained: yet we doe, at the leaſt, at euery change of Prince, change our booke of common prayers, we be ſo wanton that we know not what we would haue. I anſwer, they haue done the like, they cannot denie it, for proofe whereof I referre them to the preface which is ſet before their owne Breuiary, wherein it is ſpecified, how many times their owne Breuiary hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
               <p>It is no diſcredit, either to them, or vs, to alter for the better and to correct that which we finde amiſſe. All faults are not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied at once, neither is all truth reuealed at once. But it is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to perſeuere and continue in an error after it is found out, and not to imbrace a truth after it is reuealed. The Church had a time of growing three hundred yeares after Chriſt, being then
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177853:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> watered, and made fruitefull by the bloud of Martyrs; then the religion of <hi>Rome</hi> was found, according to that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth teſtifie in his Epiſtle to the Romanes, the Biſhops thereof <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> continued zealous, and were commonly martired. The Church had a time of floriſhing three hundred yeares, which beganne when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great granted peace vnto the goſpel, and perſecution ceaſed, ſo long found doctrine was preached. But the Church afterward beganne to decay and ſo went backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vntill <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, in whoſe time corruption began to creepe in, and ſo ranne ouer the whole body of the Church, and euery chriſtian Kingdome which were members of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo that the whole viſible Catholike Church through the world was mightily deformed. Then <hi>Luther</hi> in his time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne a reformation againe, though he reformed not the whole, yet he reformed ſome partes, like a Phygtion, which finding a mans body full of ſores, healeth ſome members, although he be not able to reſtore the whole to his firſt integritie. Neither did <hi>Luther</hi> reforme thoſe parts vnto the full, by reaſon of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his life, and the greatneſſe of the cure which he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, but left ſomewhat to be reformed after him by <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> which as they came after him, ſo they ſaw more truth then was reuealed vnto him (for it did not pleaſe God to reueale all truth to one man, or in one age.) So then, as a Phyſition which being not able to cure the whole body, cureth ſome parts and members, and yet being preuented by death, doeth not ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reſtore thoſe partes which hee cureth vnto their former ſtrength and agilitie, but leaueth his worke to be finiſhed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo did <hi>Luther</hi> by the Church. The Clergie of <hi>England</hi> therefore in King <hi>Henries</hi> dayes eſtabliſhed religion and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their ſeruice booke according to that ſmal portion and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge which then they had. In the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> and Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> more light was reuealed then before, and thoſe errours which were eſpyed, were amended. And as it was no ſhame for vs to reforme our errours when wee eſpied them; ſo it muſt needs be vnexcuſable to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to continue in their errours now they are layde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen before them, or to winke at nooneday that they will not ſee them. The Lord of his mercie through Ieſus Chriſt, giue them
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177853:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and vs his grace, that we may agree together in on truth, and as ſheep of one fold, hearken only to the voice of him which is the great Shepheard of our ſoules, which is Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                  <p>I Thought it requiſite to forbeare multitudes of quotations of places, and allegations of Doctors and Schoolemen, becauſe this Treatiſe was written for the inſtruction of the ignorant. I haue, vpon purpoſe, affected breuitie, becauſe my deſire was, that euery one ſhould reade it. Some Latine ſentences of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> I haue produced, that the Aduerſarie might not charge me as if I had falſified any thing, or dealt otherwiſe than ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. I haue alleadged thoſe places only which were ſo perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to this buſineſſe which I haue in hand as they could not be well omitted, And I haue refrained to handle ſome other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, which peraduenture would be very pleaſing to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becauſe authoritie hath not iudged it conuenient they ſhould be diſcuſſed. Let it not ſeeme ſtrange which I haue written, that the learned Papiſts flie from their ancient defences, and cleaue to ours, and that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the great <hi>Golias</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> in his works which beare a title as if they were written wholy againſt vs, doth in many points hold with vs, and in thoſe very points iuſtifie vs, wherein he is thought to condemne vs, that in very many things he is a Proteſtant, or at the leaſt, not a Papiſt, that the Roman religion is refined, for it will plainely appeare to all iudicious and indifferent readers. I haue ſpoken of this argument more at large, in mine anſwere to <hi>Bellarmines</hi> foure bookes <hi>de verbo Dei,</hi> and his fiue bookes <hi>de Chriſto,</hi> which had beene publiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time, had it not beene for the great difficultie of print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Latine bookes here in <hi>London,</hi> but are now beyond the Seas to be printed, and I will obſerue the like in the reſt of his workes, which I do intend to anſwer if God ſhal giue me life and health, and bleſſe my labours. There be many Ieſuites and Seminaries, diſperſed in this land, into whoſe handes I doubt not but this booke will come, which if they will but remember what <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> ought to be, <hi>in pectore Aaronis,</hi> in the heartes of Gods Miniſters, if they will reade without partialitie, and that I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177853:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> may vſe their owne phraſe of ſpeach, ſpeake ſincerely, and <hi>in verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> what they thinke, I ſubmit my ſelfe to their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whether I haue deliuered a truth or not; and I perſwade my ſelfe that it they haue that integritie whereof they make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they will not deny one truth to gaine many worldes. But thus much haue I written at this time, for the diſcharge of my conſcience, the zeale I beare to the truth, and the inſtruction of them which hitherto haue not vnderſtoode themſelues. I pray GOD my perſwaſion may perſwade. His Maieſtie hath profeſſed that he will eſtabliſh the truth, if he do not, that I may with reuerence and in all duty vſe his owne wordes, his bookes will witneſſe againſt him, at the latter day. He may doe it, if he be aſſiſting to his Miniſters. But he cannot do it, vnleſſe he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide that there be a learned Miniſtery through the land, that the learned be preferred before the vnlearned, they which labor in the word, before them which are idle, that they be preferred ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their worth, that they be ſufficiently prouided for, that they be countenanced by his Highneſſe, his Nobles, the gentrie, but eſpecially by the Iudges the Land, that they haue no rights denied vnto them, which of dutie they may challenge out of Gods word. And this his Maieſtie ſhall neuer effect, vnleſſe he preferre religion before policie, remooue <hi>Gehezi</hi> out of <hi>Eliſaeus</hi> his ſeruice, abandon flatterie, baniſh ſimonie out of the Church, and briberie out of his houſe and all his Courts. The Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and increaſe his zeale, that he may raigne ouer vs like <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> to Gods glory, the aduancement of the Goſpel, our happineſſe, the comfort of his owne ſoule, which he ſhall one day feele to be more precious vnto him than al his kingdomes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:177853:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Proteſtant Reader.</head>
            <p>Be it very farre from the ſeruants of God that they ſhould mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake me, or conceiue any ſiniſter opinion of my indeuors, as if I dealt too fauorably with the Papiſts. For they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of mine intent &amp; purpoſe, which is not to exaſperate and prouoke them to anger, but to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which I cannot do by bitter ſpeeches, neither yet by burdening them with any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths. The ſpirit of meeknes doth beſt become Chriſt his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the worde of God hath taught me to deale charitablie with all men, but eſpecially to reſtore them which haue fallen, by gentleneſſe, not to breake the bruſed reede, nor to quench the ſmoaking flax. That I am not of their mind this booke teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth ſufficiently enough. That I do not make more fauourable conſtructions of their Doctrine than truth and veritie doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, their doctrine it ſelfe doth ſhew. How much I diſcent from them, my Sermon doth witneſſe which I preached at S. <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe about eight yeares ſince and publiſhed in print, wherein I ſhewed that the ſtate of the Papacie was Antichriſt. In it I ſet downe, as I hope, though a briefe, yet a full and perfect ſtate of the queſtion; what was wanting in words, by reaſon of the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time, was ſupplied in ſubſtance, I anſwered all obiections out of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Sanders</hi> which were of moment, that it might be an helpe to others which ſhould aferward deliuer the ſame againe in more wordes, and larger volume. The God of al wiſdome and knowledge direct their harts and mindes to the true knowledge of his worde through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
